John.
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury,
have you reached a verdict?
We have, Your Honour.
Will the defendant please rise.
We find the defendant,
Lester Matthews, guilty of murder.
Les, we can appeal.
Les.
Thanks.
Thanks a lot.
Relax.
I can't.
You know, I used to be lucky in life.
No matter what I did,
it turned out okay.
The last couple of years have been
one lousy turn after another.
Let's go, Les. They're ready.
Les, we considered your application
for parole very carefully.
Frankly, we were impressed.
Your war record in Vietnam,
the fact that you remained a partner
with the Dacoma Corporation.
But most importantly,
your exemplary record here in
the seven years since your conviction.
Look, John Colter was my best friend
and my partner. I did not murder him.
The issue here is
your qualifications for parole,
not the circumstances
of your conviction.
Now, on that basis,
parole is granted.
Thank you. Thank you.
I told you.
Yeah,
I guess my luck's changing, huh?
I'm really happy for you, Les.
I really am.
Thanks, pal. Thanks a lot.
Hey, lighten up, Eli.
Look, you'll be out of here in no time.
Come on. Eighteen months
is like a lifetime in this joint.
I won't forget you, Les.
I won't let you.
Look, I'll have a job waiting for you
when you get out.
You mean that?
Would I lie to you?
I've never been anything but a thief,
and not a very good one.
Hey, trust me, would you?
Now, get back to work before
I change my mind.
Hey, leave him alone.
Go on, Eli. Get out of here.
- Hear you made parole, huh?
- What do you care?
I just came to say goodbye.
Drop it, Matthews.
Now, listen.
My newspaper is supposed
to be wrapped in plastic when it rains.
I don't care if it was clear
when you delivered it.
You can listen to the weather report.
I've been subscribing to your paper
for over 30 years
and my money's as good as
anybody else's for a dry newspaper.
You ought to see this.
I can barely make out the front page.
- Law offices.
- Charlene.
Dad, where are you? You have
the Johnson deposition in minutes.
Charlene, listen. Cancel.
- Well, we cancelled it twice last week.
- Cancel it again.
Do this for me:
Go in the storage room,
dig out the files on one of
my old cases, Lester Matthews.
The Lester Matthews?
The one in the morning paper?
- Yes.
- I didn't know you represented him.
I tried.
Oh, that's the one you lost.
- Dad?
- Just dig out the files, will you?
I'll be there in a few hours.
Mr. Dolan.
- Mr. Matlock.
- Stopped by to see Les Matthews.
Well, we've already
got a lawyer for him.
Would you mind if I spent
a few minutes with him?
- Suit yourself.
- Thanks.
Hey, Bob.
Hey, what brings you out
on this miserable day?
I understand you're holding
Les Matthews for trial.
- So?
- I'd like to see him.
Now, you're not his lawyer.
Bob, for old times' sake, fill me in.
Well, a couple of inmates
witnessed a stabbing.
When did convicted felons
become strong witnesses?
A guard saw it too.
You got a motive?
- I'm late for an arraignment.
- Well, Bob,
it just doesn't make sense.
A man a few days from parole
committing cold-blooded murder
like that.
That's not my problem.
And Ben, it's not yours either.
Hello, Les.
- What are you doing here?
- I've got a little pull with the jailer.
Les, I know how angry you are
that I lost your case.
Look, why don't you get out of here?
Sam already got me a lawyer.
For what it's worth,
I never forgot your case.
It's like an itch I can't scratch.
Somehow, somewhere,
I missed something,
something that would've
turned it around.
You earned $1 00,000.
Maybe you lost a few nights' sleep.
I've been in this joint
for seven years.
Now get out of here.
What I hear, you're looking at life
unless you get the best lawyer
you can find.
Now, I know you're angry
and I don't blame you.
What is it with you? For seven years,
I haven't heard from you
and all of a sudden you show up
looking for work? What--?
For seven years, there was
there was nothing I could do.
Maybe now there is.
I'd like the chance.
Mr. Matlock, there's a guy out there
who says he's his lawyer.
Yeah?
What's it going to be, Les?
He's mistaken.
Mr. Matlock's my attorney.
It's past your bedtime.
What are you doing here?
I'm working on the case,
but my toenail got caught in my sock,
so I'm working on my toenail.
You go ahead.
I'm waiting for Tyler, anyway.
Since I got started with this,
I think I'll just finish it off.
Go ahead.
Okay.
- I went over the Les Matthews trial.
- A miscarriage of justice.
Another way of saying
you hate being beaten.
Charlene, I've got this feeling.
Well, let's look at the facts.
Les Matthews caught his partner
John Colter
stealing $50,000 from their company
in order to pay off his gambling debts.
- Right.
- The two of them
had a violent argument,
which dozens of people saw.
- Right.
- Later that night, Colter was found
shot to death in his home
and they found the murder weapon
at Matthews' house.
- The man didn't even have an alibi.
- That's right.
Well, now, if I'd been on the jury,
I'd have convicted.
Well, you'd of been wrong.
Daddy, every once in a while,
it's all right to lose.
Charlene, these three partners
were Vietnam veterans.
They had a dream.
They started a business.
They were best friends.
Les Matthews didn't kill
his best friend over $50,000.
Even if that's true, that's not the case
we're going to try.
- This one is a lot tougher.
- Maybe, maybe not.
Well, you sure took your sweet time.
Well, the guy I was looking for
doesn't hang out on street corners.
Well?
All the news sheds a slightly
different light on this case.
As you know, the con that got iced,
Mr. Lashley, was doing life
for committing two murders,
but they weren't just ordinary murders.
They were contract hits for the mob.
So he's not likely to kill
without getting paid.
Not likely.
Maybe somebody
didn't want Les Matthews
to come out of prison alive.
Like who?
Maybe the same person
who put him there to start with.
Tyler...
...you know this is important to me.
Yes.
We need some answers
out of prison.
So, what do you want me to do?
Send out a questionnaire?
Did I ever tell you that the warden
and I went to college together?
No. Why?
Hold it. Face forward.
Strip.
Hey, dimwit.
Your sheet doesn't say
that you're deaf.
Strip.
Hold it.
D Block,
C Range, Cell 1 3. You're in here.
Hey, look, did the--
The warden talk to you about me?
No, but if you give me any trouble,
your head will land on his desk.
Now get in there.
Come on.
I'm Tyler.
Lester.
- Just like old times, huh?
- I hope not.
Me too.
Daddy,
I can't reach John Colter's widow.
She won't return my calls.
- Charlene Matlock.
- Hi, Les Matthews.
Case A981 04,
State of Georgia
v. Lester Matthews.
Benjamin Matlock for the defence,
Your Honour.
Defendant waives the reading
of the complaint,
has been advised of his
constitutional rights, time is waived.
I'm setting this case
for January 1 7th at 9 a.m.
If this courthouse hasn't
floated away by then.
- Prosecution agrees?
- Yes, Your Honour.
- Mr. Matlock?
- Fine with me, Your Honour.
Thank you, gentlemen.
I'll call the next case in just a moment.
Les.
Hey, Rog.
I thought you could use
some moral support.
Oh, Rog Bundy. This is Ben Matlock.
This is his daughter Charlene.
- How do you do?
- Pleasure.
Look, if there's anything you need,
please let me know.
- I appreciate it. I gotta go.
- I'll see you in a bit.
Actually, we met before
at Les' last trial.
- That's right.
- You were assisting Les.
You've got quite a memory.
Who do you assist now?
I'm--
I'm the treasurer of the company.
Look,
everything I've got I owe to Les.
Mr. Matlock, you have got
to get him off this time.
That's the plan.
Sorry to keep you waiting.
- Bad day, huh?
- Very.
Les missed you in court.
- I was busy.
- Yeah.
My daughter says the company's
quadrupled in size.
Well, business is great.
What can I do for you?
Well, you're Les' partner, Mr. Dolan,
and I was wondering
if you have any idea
why someone would want
to keep him in prison.
I don't follow you.
Well, it's true that you
and John Colter's widow
would inherit his share
of the company if he should die.
- That's true.
- Yeah.
Yeah, I have a theory
that the man Les stabbed
was hired to kill him
by someone on the outside.
I get the feeling you think it was me.
Well, I could make a case for it.
You live an expensive life:
houses, cars, travel.
A life you can't quite afford since
you have borrowed liberally
from the bank account that holds
Les' share of the profits.
Les knows all about that.
You know, if I had a legal
and binding agreement
that forced me to give up
large sums of money
that could've been mine
to someone who didn't earn it
and couldn't spend it,
I might become bitter.
I'm tired of you, Mr. Matlock.
Seven years ago,
you thought I betrayed Les,
and now it's the same thing.
Les Matthews is my friend.
I'd proven it time and again,
and I don't have to justify it to you.
Well,
that remains to be seen.
There's your subpoena.
You know, I think Les made
a dreadful mistake hiring you.
Well,
maybe he thinks
I'll get it right this time.
What the hell?
Where is it?
- Hey.
- Hey, what's happening here?
- Back off, man.
- Where's the book?
I told you I don't know.
You've gotta believe me.
Back off.
Hey, man. Are you all right?
Hey, come on, get up here.
There you go.
I've gotta get out of this place.
Look, those guys
do not read Shakespeare.
What kind of book
are they talking about?
You don't want to know.
Our cell is torn apart.
That guy almost stabbed me
with a shiv.
Now, I wanna know.
Okay. Lashley, the guy who died,
he was the top con in the joint.
And he had this book
with all his contacts:
drugs, payoffs,
outside sources, everything.
Well, the book is missing.
- You know where that book is?
- No.
- Miss Colter?
- Yes?
Ben Matlock.
- Come in, Mr. Matlock.
- Thank you.
Thanks for answering my call.
For a while there,
I thought you were avoiding me.
Why would I do that?
Oh, I remember that clock.
It's beautiful.
A clock like that should be kept up.
Oh, it probably needs repair.
Were you here before?
Yes. I was here the day
after your husband died.
Mr. Matlock, you know,
I resented you seven years ago
when you defended
my husband's killer.
And I don't really understand
what you're doing here now.
Excuse me?
What do you want?
I've never been able to get your
husband's death out of my mind.
How have you been?
It's been difficult.
I loved him and I miss him.
Well, I'm-- I'm sorry.
Seven years is a long time.
There's been no one else?
No one like him.
- Well, at least he left you--
- Money?
That doesn't buy me what I want.
Is that all you wanted to know,
Mr. Matlock?
- Yes.
- I see.
- And thank you.
- Goodbye, Mr. Matlock.
Thanks. Is--
Is that today's newspaper?
Mine got away from me,
and if you're not using it...
No, it's not today's.
Thank you.
Where's my book?
It's gonna be all right, man.
You'll see.
- You, against the wall now.
- Man-- Man, get a doctor.
- Hold me.
- You're all right. Okay.
What are you doing here?
You don't live
at that other house, do you?
Andrea, who is it?
May I come in?
We've been together a long time.
How long?
- Almost six years.
- Six years.
We began seeing each other
about a year after John died,
only nobody knows.
That's why Andrea lied.
That's a long time
for a secret like that.
Mr. Matlock,
look at it from my point of view.
I get Les Matthews' job,
fall in love with John Colter's widow.
It's a little awkward.
So you keep your home as a front.
That's right.
Well, if you want people
to really believe you live there,
you'd better get some new magazines
and wind your clocks.
Les appreciated
your coming to court.
- You were there?
- Yes.
I have never believed
that Les killed John Colter.
I was in Vietnam
with the three of them.
They were friends.
- And that's how you know Les.
- Yes.
And that's how he brought you
into the business?
That's right.
You know, it's kind of--
It's kind of like an old movie plot.
It's interesting.
In the movies, towards the end,
we know about the man
and the woman and that
the man has his friend's job,
but that's just the tip of the iceberg.
Later, there's another revelation.
That's how they keep your interest
to the end.
So did you do it?
No, I didn't do it.
Well, I'd better be going.
We're in court in the morning.
- Maybe I'Il-- Maybe I'll see you there.
- Goodbye, Mr. Matlock.
Bye.
Well, here...
Officer Greene, on December 2nd
at precisely 3 p.m.,
did you respond to the sounds of a
fight coming from the prison library?
- Yes, sir, I did.
- Please tell the court what you saw.
As I entered the library,
I saw an inmate, Mr. Matthews,
lying over Wayne Lashley
with a shiv in his hand.
He had just stabbed him.
I show you People's Exhibit 5
and ask if you recognise it.
Yes, sir, I do.
That's the weapon I took
from Lester Matthews.
- Nothing further.
- Cross-examine.
Officer Green,
you are familiar
with the defendant's prison record?
Yes, sir. It's excellent.
In fact, he had just won parole,
hadn't he?
- Yes.
- In your long prison experience,
have you ever heard of an inmate
who's just won his parole,
committing cold-blooded murder
while he's still in prison?
- No, sir, I haven't.
- Well, let me ask you this.
You testified that
you saw the defendant
holding a knife over the victim.
- That's right.
- But you didn't actually
see the defendant stab the victim.
No, sir, but it looked like--
I'm not interested in what it looked
like, Mr. Green, just what you saw.
Now, as far as you know,
Mr. Lashley could've attacked
Mr. Matthews.
There could've been a struggle.
Mr. Matthews could've killed him
in self-defence.
- Your Honour, objection. Speculation.
- No further questions.
Mr. Lashley went into the library
and asked Mr. Matthews for a book,
and Mr. Matthews pulled out a knife
and stabbed him.
Did you try and stop him?
Yeah, I tried, but it all happened
so fast, there was nothing I could do.
No further questions.
Mr. Matlock?
He's lying.
Mr. Foley,
did you go to the library
with Mr. Lashley and Mr. Lipton?
Yeah, that's right.
Well, why did the three of you
go to the library?
- To get some books.
- I see.
Was there something in particular
you were interested in reading?
Well, I was gonna look around.
How about, would you mind reading
that right there to the court?
- Yeah, I would.
- Objection, Your Honour.
No relevancy. I fail to see the point
of this demonstration.
- You will in a second.
- Mr. Foley, please read the book.
There you go.
I can't.
- You can't?
- No.
Are you saying you can't read?
Yeah. So what? I read the pictures.
Isn't it true you did not go to the library
for a book?
- No.
- Isn't it true
you were one of Wayne Lashley's
errand boys?
- No.
- Isn't it true
he ordered you
to guard the library door
while he attempted to kill
Les Matthews?
That's a bunch of bull--
Isn't it true you're serving a life term for
armed robbery and a double murder
and perjury means nothing to you?
No further questions.
Redirect?
No, Your Honour.
Ben, level with me, will you?
We're not getting anywhere, are we?
Well, we're making some points,
and my people
are working day and night.
Thanks.
Oh, that would be very helpful.
If you--
Okay, as long as it's someone
that you know and that's reliable.
All right. Thanks a lot. Bye.
Dad?
What?
- You look terrible.
- Thanks.
Daddy, I'm gonna call
a CP in the morning.
I've been all through
these company books.
Sam Dolan made them a fortune.
Now, I'm no expert,
but somehow, someway,
there's a lot less money here
than there ought to be.
Did Tyler call?
Not yet.
Hope he's all right.
Hey, take the bottom bunk.
Here.
Say, I owe you. You saved my life.
You wanna repay me?
Give me that book.
I don't trust anyone here.
You can trust me.
Eli, you're gonna
have to trust someone.
Bundy.
Hello?
Well...
...now we know Roger Bundy's
private number
was in Wayne Lashley's
little black book.
Well, that still doesn't prove
he paid Lashley to kill Les.
- I know.
- Now, wait a minute.
You mean I spent all that time
in prison, risked my life for nothing?
Not exactly.
If Mr. Bundy's our boy,
he didn't commit one murder.
He committed two.
- Mr. Matlock.
- Yes, ma'am.
Thank you
for agreeing to see me here.
You sounded so urgent
on the phone.
Well, it was a night just like tonight
that your husband was murdered.
- It was raining.
- That's right.
Now, what was so urgent,
Mr. Matlock?
You and Mr. Bundy didn't tell me
the whole truth when we spoke.
- We didn't?
- No. A couple of things.
Six weeks before your husband died,
you and Mr. Bundy
were in Bermuda at the same time.
In fact, you were on the same airplane.
Was that a coincidence?
Why did you lie
about when the affair began?
I thought that we should tell everybody
the truth.
Exactly what is that?
My testimony at Les Matthews'
trial was true.
I did come home
and find John's body.
The house was dark.
It was thundering.
- But when--
- You called the police?
I was about to call the police.
Roger arrived.
And he was drenched from the rain.
He said that he had-- Had a drink
earlier in the day with Les Matthews
and that he'd come over
to talk with John.
He was hoping to make peace
between Les and John.
Why didn't you tell anyone
he was here?
Because if anyone knew
we were having an affair,
we would've looked guilty.
I want you to think back.
Did you see his car come up?
My husband had just been killed.
But you waited for the car to leave
to call the police?
Yes, I did.
- Did you see the car?
- No.
Roger wasn't in the habit
of parking near the house
when he came to see me.
But that night
he didn't come to see you.
He came to see your husband.
Now, I want you to tell me
exactly what happened when he left.
He walked to the door,
gave me a kiss
and said not to worry and left.
Did you watch him go?
Yes. I could see his umbrella
go down the street.
And that was it,
you called the police?
Mr. Matlock, no matter what we did,
I know Les Matthews
killed my husband.
Well, it's taken seven years,
but I think
I'm gonna prove you wrong.
Come to court tomorrow.
It might be interesting.
How long have you known
Les Matthews?
About 1 7 years.
In fact, you served
in Vietnam with him, didn't you?
- Yes, I did.
- Now, when was that?
1 970 to '7 1 .
And when Les Matthews
came home in 1 97 1 ,
you stayed on for another tour,
didn't you?
Yes.
According to your military record,
you were in the 3rd Battalion
of the 1 01 st Airborne Division.
- Right?
- That's right.
Did you know a fellow
named Wayne Lashley?
- No, I didn't.
- Are you sure?
Yes.
The reason I sound sceptical
is because I have his military record
right here,
and during 1 97 1 and '72,
he served in your outfit.
You sure you didn't know him?
I just told you I didn't.
Okay. Let me ask you this then.
You're the treasurer and chief financial
officer of the Dacoma Corporation.
- Is that right?
- That's right.
And you have a private telephone
in your office?
Yes.
And let's see, the number is 555-6960.
Is that right?
Yes.
I bet you wonder
how I got that number.
Well, I'll tell you.
I got it out of this little black book.
And oddly enough, this book
was owned by Wayne Lashley.
Now, how do you suppose
your private, unlisted number
wound up in this convicted murderer's
telephone book?
I don't know.
- You still insist you didn't know him.
- That's right.
I won't belabour the point.
We'll move on to something else.
Seven years ago when your friend,
the defendant, Les Matthews,
went to prison, you took over his job
as chief financial officer
of the Dacoma Corporation, right?
That's right.
Now in that time,
the business has done very well.
So have you.
I have bank statements that show
that you have accumulated
$4.2 million in six different accounts.
Well, we...
We have some excellent
investment portfolios.
You know,
since I defended Les Matthews
on a charge of murder
seven years ago,
I've always felt like I missed
something, some kind of thread.
Well, Mr. Bundy,
you have done me the great service
of showing me I didn't miss anything.
Seven years ago,
there was nothing to miss.
There was nothing to find.
But now, I found it.
Your Honour,
I'd like to enter into evidence
this statement
and supporting documents
from a certified public accountant
showing that in the past seven years,
exactly $4.2 million have been stolen
from the Dacoma Corporation
by financial manipulation
of its books.
You stole that money, didn't you?
No.
You killed John Colter so you
could steal that money, didn't you?
- No.
- Objection.
We are here to try Les Matthews
for the murder of Wayne Lashley.
We are not here to retry a murder
he has already been found guilty of.
Your Honour,
may we approach the bench?
Your Honour, I believe I have evidence
showing that these two murders
are inextricably linked together.
But Your Honour, as I just said,
Les Matthews has already be--
Burton.
Burton don't you want to find the truth?
Yes, Ben. Of course I do,
but the past is the past.
Gentlemen,
no fighting in this courtroom.
Your Honour,
I honestly believe this is the only way
we'll ever discover the truth.
Well, very well, Mr. Matlock,
but I warn you: Get to the point.
Objection overruled.
Proceed, Mr. Matlock.
Mr. Bundy, isn't it true that you
were having an affair with Mrs. Colter
for almost a year
before her husband was murdered?
Yes.
In fact, only a moment
after she discovered the body,
you came into her house, didn't you?
- Yes.
- And you both decided
it would be wise for you to leave
before she called the police.
- Yes.
- Why was that?
Because we thought
we might be considered suspects.
When you came into the house,
you were drenched
as if you had been
standing out in the rain unprotected.
It was raining very hard.
And yet when you left,
you had your umbrella.
Now, Mrs. Colter
will be glad to testify that you did.
What was your umbrella
doing there?
I don't know. I...
I must've left it there
a couple of days before.
Well,
you don't usually carry an umbrella
on a warm sunny day, do you?
I suspect not.
And you're sure you left it there
a couple of days before?
Couldn't have been a week,
maybe two?
Well, you know, it might have been
a couple of weeks before.
Mr. Bundy,
there are two things
I remember about August 1 979:
One was John Colter's murder.
The other, my garden died.
We had a drought that summer.
Your Honour, I have a headline here
from the Atlanta Examiner
dated August 1 0th,1 979, the morning
after John Colter was murdered.
And the headline reads, and I quote:
''Surprise storm
ends eight-week-Iong drought.''
Now, why was your umbrella
at the Colter house during a drought?
You know, those warm sunny days
we have here in Atlanta.
I don't know. I...
It probably
was some kind of a mistake.
I'll tell you why.
You went to see John Colter
before his wife came home
the night of August 9th.
It was raining,
you had your umbrella.
You shot him.
You heard someone drive up.
You ran out the French doors.
No umbrella.
You got drenched.
Then you saw it was Andrea
who had come home.
Then you realised
you forgot your umbrella.
So you went around
to the front of the house,
came in the front door--
You killed him! You killed John!
- No, I didn't.
- Yes, you did.
Seven years ago,
you saw your opportunity to clean up.
You knew Sam Dolan
couldn't add a column of figures.
So when Les Matthews
got in a fight with John Colter,
you saw your opportunity
to get rid of both of them
and steal to your heart's content.
But when Les Matthews
won his parole,
you knew he'd come home
and discover your thefts.
So you contacted your old army buddy,
Wayne Lashley,
and you hired him to kill
Les Matthews.
Only it backfired.
My client killed him in self-defence.
Isn't that the way it happened?
No.
I believe with the help of Mrs. Colter,
the good officers of the
Atlanta Police Department will prove it.
The defence rests.
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury,
have you reached a verdict?
We have, Your Honour.
We find the defendant,
Lester Matthews, not guilty.
- Thank you.
- Don't thank me. Thank him.
- Yeah. Thank me.
- Thank you very...
www.tvsubtitles.net